It's 1100 AD. France isn't a very united
country yet, and if the king fails to
pull it together, France doesn't become
a superpower and could end up fragmented
like the Holy Roman Empire.
With the chaos caused by the breakup of
the kingdom post Charlemagne behind it,
France through the following High Middle
Ages was an increasingly unified and
outward-looking nation.
However, there was still much work to be
done. The consolidation by the Capetian
dynasty, who had drawn power to the
center and away from regional nobles,
helped lay the foundations for the next
chapter. These were the defining
centuries, which included the Age of the
Crusades, as well as early large-scale
internal European conflict in the form
of the Hundred Years' War, emerging
chivalric codes, majestic Gothic
architecture, and the first organized
military taries and administrations
would also occur in this defining period
for France, an era which would
ultimately launch her into the Age of
the Ancient Regime, global exploration,
and the Reformation.
France at the turn of the 12th century
was emerging increasingly as a nation,
but its borders and authority were still
a patchwork far from the modern outline
and was increasingly defined by
differences with its neighbors and was
ruled by a Christian king attempting to
centralize power. However, it was still
a fragmented kingdom with regional
authorities continuing to hold
significant power in places. The process
would take some time. By 1100, Europe
was firmly in the High Medieval Era with
a transformation having taken place
since the time of Charlemagne's rule
some 300 years previous, an agricultural
revolution, including in plowing
technology, had dramatically increased
yields, which in turn supported larger
populations.
This, combined with urbanization, to
swell countless cities through the
region, creating population hubs served
by more infrastructure and increasing
labor specialization within them. But,
bigger populations also meant bigger
pressure on land, on lords, and on
kings.
For many of France's peasants, the 11th
to 13th century were, in fact, easier
than during the late medieval period.
Due to increases in productivity and
output, many were able to negotiate
better terms with the landowners they
rented from, with some leaving serfdom
altogether for the expanding cities. The
use of a heavier plow, which rested
across animals' shoulders rather than
necks, as a result of an innovative new
harness design, meant tracts of new land
were opened up for farming, which had
previously been considered too rocky.
This, again, increased food supply,
which combined with the proliferation of
water and windmills throughout France
during the period. These mills slashed
the labor required to turn grains into
flour, transforming a key process in
staple food production. The violence
which had so plagued West Francia in
centuries prior, through both external
Viking raids and internal conflict, was
also on the decline. Many of the Viking
raiders had now settled in Normandy,
becoming stakeholders in the region, and
movements like the Peace and Truce of
God had contributed to a more general
reduction in violence across society.
This more stable platform allowed other
areas to flourish, which included the
economy. It had
transitioned away from a subsistence and
bartering foundation to a more
mercantile approach with broader
regional trade networks. This increased
affluence gave rise to more investments,
businesses, and jobs servicing these.
All of this meant a very different
operating environment for the population
of 1100's Francia. And in a calmer
world, kings could finally plan
long-term.
King Louis the VI was another early
Capetian who made great efforts to
centralize power, a key precursor to the
emergence of a modern nation. This was
often achieved through force and a more
conflictual approach with his subjects,
which may have created animosity, but
served to increase royal authority.
These actions included taking on the
robber barons who were powerful regional
landowners operating with impunity
within their territories. His success in
reigning in these elements is symbolic
of this broader tussle across not just
West Francia, but much of wider Europe.
The high point of local nobles' power
had been reached. This was a new age of
monarchic top-down control where nobles
were to know their place as below the
king and never equal to him. Of
significance, Louis was also among the
first Capetian monarchs to issue
ordinances intended to apply beyond his
own royal domain, reaching wider parts
of the kingdom. The precursor to royal
decrees issued over the subjects of
France, they were another stepping stone
on the road to nationhood. But every
push from the crown created enemies.
This was the age of the Crusades, which
were of great significance to West
Francia.
The period from 1147 to 1270 saw seven
of the major crusades, the second
through the eighth, with much of the
religious fervor, manpower, and supplies
for them originating in France.
The geopolitical implications for the
Levant region aside, for the emerging
French nation, they helped deepen the
place of religion in society, cementing
national identity in the face of a
foreign Islamic adversary as well as
contributing to a more outward-looking
worldview. The crusades furthered the
military capabilities of the nation,
providing lessons through combat and
giving rise to more organized forces,
which would prove key to the wars of the
coming centuries. It was also a means to
channel violence outwards against
external enemies, which otherwise may
have manifested internally. When
combined with the previously mentioned
peace and truce of God movements, it
helped further solidify internal
stability, an important precursor to
effective nation-building. And once you
build an army for Jerusalem, you can use
it at home, too. Another significant
reign was that of Philip II between 1180
and 1223.
Grandson to the reformer Louis the Sick,
he would oversee more centralization
with the power of regional barons and
nobles further reduced, as well as deal
with the grave threat from the English
and their Angevin Empire.
The Angevin Empire was not a single
unified state. It was a cross-channel
patchwork of lands personally ruled by
the Plantagenet kings of England,
especially Henry II from 1154 and his
sons, built through inheritance and
Henry's 1152 marriage to Eleanor of
Aquitaine.
It included England plus huge French
fiefs such as Normandy, Anjou, and
Aquitaine.
Meaning the King of England was also a
duke and count inside France.
The catch was feudal. For those French
lands in feudal law, he owed homage to
the King of France. So, France's most
dangerous neighbor was technically also
its vassal. At the time of Philip's
ascent to the throne, the Angevins
comprised large portions of France. With
his success at the Battle of Bouvines in
1214, he reasserted French control over
a large area, bolstered his own royal
authority greatly, and severely weakened
his English rivals for a period.
Alongside his reforms and development of
the state, he oversaw a period of
economic prosperity and growth of the
middle class.
All of this helps to transform France
into the dominant power in Europe of the
period.
From the late 12th century onward, he
also increasingly titled himself King of
France rather than the Franks, another
sign of the development of the nation.
One victory, and suddenly the map of
Europe changed.
The tussle between regional and central
power in this period can also be seen in
the infamous Albigensian Crusade,
which occurred between 1209 and 1229.
Overtly, it aimed to destroy the dualist
Christian Cathar sect, which had gained
a strong following in Southern France.
However, it also very much served the
material purpose of reducing regional
power and extending the influence of the
monarch.
The area in which the Cathar group was
strongest was administered by previously
autonomous local leaders, including
Count Raymond of Toulouse,
here crown authority had been marginal,
and Raymond generally followed a policy
of pragmatic tolerance, allowing the
Cathars space to practice their faith,
often tied to asceticism and apostolic
ideals.
It was a strict and uncompromising
religious movement, sharply at odds with
the Catholic Church's top-down and
centralized approach.
This provided all the more reason for
the Church in Rome to want to crush the
Cathars,
as having it spread further from its
heartlands could in time pose an
existential risk to the central Catholic
Church.
Hence the bloody alliance in their
crusade with Pope and northern French
nobles, with the French crown later
intervening more directly under Louis
VIII, which remains one of the cruelest
internal European campaigns in history.
The holy war is fought inside France. In
the wake of the devastation wrought by
the crusade, widespread civilian
suffering at the hands of the crusader
armies made the job of reasserting royal
authority in the chaos which followed
simpler.
In this way, large parts of the south,
from Albi to Toulouse, were made far
more loyal crown dependencies. So,
whether gained through warfare with a
peer state, as in the Angevin saga, or
through crusading against one's own
population, as in the Cathar case, both
led to the same result of increasing the
power of the crown and cementing the
monarchic basis of the state. By the
time of the reign of Louis IX, the
benefits of these bloody years were
being felt, with much of the south now
absorbed under royal authority and the
English king finally recognizing the
French crown's authority over the Duchy
of Aquitaine, essentially Guyenne and
Gascony, held as a French fief, Louis
would become the most significant
landowner in France. After that,
internally, he would oversee a host of
reforms in legal and civic areas,
helping establish the precedent for a
monarch's increasing role here. These
included the phasing out of trials by
ordeal, where a guilty or innocent
verdict was achieved through varying
degrees of torture, the expansion of
royal bailiff offices, as well as the
principle of presumption of innocence in
French law. Through his remarkably long
reign, King Louis would also oversee a
renaissance in French society with
magnificent feats of architecture
constructed, including defining Gothic
cathedrals of the era. Regarded as a
fair and pious ruler, he was also
respected throughout Europe. All of this
contributed to France reaching the peak
of its medieval power and influence
during this period.
A pioneering nation in Europe leading
the way while others remain fragmented
territories or in the case of England
with a monarch freshly reined in by the
Magna Carta. Externally though, Louis
had less success. His attempts during
the Seventh Crusade ended in disaster
with him captured and eventually
ransomed back.
And it was during the Eighth Crusade
that he would die of dysentery in 1270
at Tunis.
It was a tragedy for the French. The
crusading curse would remain with his
son, Philip III, who would likewise die
during the Aragonese Crusade in Aragon.
However, his son, successor Philip IV,
would enjoy more success.
Carrying on the legacy of his
grandfather Louis the ninth, he expanded
and strengthened the Parliament of
France and carried out a wide range of
other reforms. He made pioneering use of
early civil servants to further rein in
the power and wealth of regional nobles,
which further boosted the power of the
monarch. By taking a much more active
role in the dispensing and control of
feudal privileges, primarily land
granted to regional nobles, he was
further able to make the role of monarch
unchallengeable and pave the way for a
fully centralized early modern state. As
part of this consolidation of power, he
also attempted to eradicate the Knights
Templar, a powerful crusading era
organization which had amassed a great
deal of wealth and power in France at
the time.
Accused of heresy, among other things,
large numbers were subsequently put to
death.
This included their leader, Jacques de
Molay, who was burned at the stake on
the Île aux Juifs in the Seine in Paris.
These charges were more than likely
cover for the real motive, which was a
power grab by King Philip and removal of
another semi-autonomous group, not to
mention he owed the group significant
amounts of money.
With the Templars mostly gone, dynastic
winds of change were blowing in again,
though.
Just as the mighty Carolingian line of
Charlemagne before it, the Capetians
time in power, too, was coming to an
end. It had enjoyed over 340 years as
the ruling house of France. However, the
death of Charles the fourth in 1328,
with no male heir, meant the line was
terminated. He was succeeded by first
cousin Philip VI from the rival Valois
dynasty. This new royal house would
continue to provide the monarchs of
France for more than 250 years until
their own suppression by the Bourbon
house, the last royal line of
consequence for France leading right up
to the days of the revolution. But more
on that later in the series. And then
comes the war that will chew France up
for over a century. Not long after this
dynastic shift, a major confrontation
was brewing with its rival, England. The
kings of England still held territory
inside France, and for those lands they
were technically vassals and owed homage
to the French king. That arrangement,
formalized in 1259, meant constant
friction over rights, courts, power, and
control. Because a sovereign king in
England could still be summoned as a
duke in France. Then, the dynastic fuse
caught fire in 1328 when Charles IV died
without a male heir. The French crown
was passed to Philip VI, but Edward III
of England had a strong blood claim
through his mother Isabella, Charles's
sister. Edward initially accepted Philip
and did homage in 1329, but disputes
over the English-held Duchy of
Aquitaine, Guyenne, and Gascony, and
royal authority escalated until Philip
moved to confiscate Edward's French
lands in 1337.
In response, Edward went to war, and in
1340 revived his claim to the French
throne, turning a legal feud into open
war. What had been small-scale conflicts
between the parties in the 1200s would
soon turn into large-scale pitched
battles with the breakout of the Hundred
Years' War. This conflict was a bloody
new chapter of European warfare
involving the deployment of larger
armies and large-scale use of new
components such as the English
longbowmen. In the early phase, French
hopes were shaken by defeat at sea and
disaster on land with a naval defeat at
Sluys in 1340 and then things would take
a turn at the Battle of Crécy. Edward
III's army deployed defensively on a
gentle slope north of the town. Infantry
and archers were positioned to cover the
entire distance between Crécy and
Wadancourt. King Edward maintained
overall control from the rear intending
to force the enemy to attack on
unfavorable terms. The English army
numbered up to 15,000 men. The French
army under Philip the VI may have been
twice that size. Pressed by
circumstances and the overconfidence of
its troops, the king chose not to rest
for the night and attacked immediately.
First sent forward were the Genoese
crossbowmen who engaged the Welsh and
English longbowmen from the lower
ground. Conditions for these mercenaries
were far from ideal and they soon
retreated. Advancing behind them was the
first detachments of French men-at-arms
who forced their way through the
Italians without regard for their
allies. This confusion combined with the
uphill charge, potholes, mud, and
raining projectiles contributed to a
disorganized attack. Units entered the
field in an uneven sequence crowding the
low ground below the English position
and reducing cohesion at the moment of
contact. French cavalry charged
repeatedly while sustaining continuous
archery fire. Horses fell, formations
broke apart, and subsequent waves
collided with those already in retreat
or disorder.
The attacks failed to gain momentum, and
the fighting devolved into brutal close
combat.
As the battle continued, the fields
became increasingly congested with
fallen men and animals. King Philip
himself narrowly escaped death. By
nightfall, resistance had collapsed. The
French force was decimated in large part
by devastating English longbow fire.
With a significant portion of the army
wiped out, it would take decades for
France to regain the initiative in this
long-running conflict. The merciless
slaughter at Crécy, with wave after wave
of French mounted knights cut down by
bow fire or by dismounted English
men-at-arms if they had the stamina to
reach enemy lines, can be seen as an
interesting turning point, not just in
the conflict, but for the broader age of
chivalry, which had existed through
Europe.
This included romantic chivalric
literature, which had dominated French
society through the 12th and 13th
centuries, alongside ideals of knightly
honor, responsibility towards the weak,
and epitomized by French kings like
Louis the Ninth.
It also saw the rapid rise of
tournaments and jousting, with events
around these activities becoming parts
of the social fabric.
There was none of this honor or
one-on-one combat idealism with
increasingly mechanized slaughter,
though.
The nature of warfare had changed, with
the need for knights gradually reduced
in favor of large standing armies, and
with it the erosion of much of the
accompanying culture. The arrival of the
Black Death in France in 1347 also aided
this process, reshaping society with
around a third to perhaps half of the
total European population killed by it
between 1347 and 1352. Despite the
carnage, France would recover and by the
1370s be back on the ascent in the
long-running conflict with the English.
As if war wasn't enough, the plague
arrives. These pivotal centuries had
seen the rise of the new Capetian ruling
dynasty and their successful efforts in
consolidating power.
This in turn helped bolster a central
state and lay the groundwork for the
early modern nation. It had been a
period of contrasts, too, with a focus
on a reduction in societal violence
through movements like the Peace and
Truce of God, but also great
bloodletting with internal campaigns
such as the merciless Albigensian
Crusade.
A cultural renaissance in France
documented in Gothic architecture, yet a
period of mass slaughter on the killing
fields of the Hundred Years' War.
Undoubtedly, though, from this period of
torment and transformation had emerged a
bedrock of a modern nation-state. A
French kingdom ruled centrally by a
Christian monarch who, now, for the most
part, has the loyalty of his regional
nobles. This was the basis on which
France would engage with the world
through the remaining medieval period,
her bitter wars with England and the
incoming age of empire.
France did not rise in a straight line.
At one point, the kingdom came so close
to collapse that a treaty tried to hand
its crown to England. Then, in the
middle of siege, plague, and civil
hatred, a young outsider walks into
history and the direction of the war
shifts. But, that was only the first
shot. Because, when the fighting with
England finally fades, France does not
find peace. It finds something worse, a
country at war with itself. So, how does
a battered, divided France turn into a
global empire? And what did it cost to
get there? The transformative period
from the late 14th to the 17th centuries
saw France emerging from the devastation
of the Hundred Years War and building a
recovery into the new dynamic era of the
Renaissance. However, conflict was never
far away. And with the emergence of
Protestantism, new Europe-wide wars of
religion would take another devastating
toll on the nation. However, by the late
16th century, with Henry the IV on the
throne, a policy of religious
toleration, formalized in the Edict of
Nantes, helped stabilize internal
dynamics and launch France into the
colonial era and a new outward-looking
global age. Emerging from years of a
brutal plague and in the midst of the
Hundred Years War with rival England,
these were trying times for the nation.
The Treaty of Brittany in 1360 brought
brief respite from the conflict and time
for France to lick her wounds from
crushing defeats at Crécy and Poitiers
over the preceding years, until war
resumed in 1369. With the reign of John
the II giving way to Charles V, France,
though, would see its fortunes rise.
Charles successfully recaptured much of
the territory previously taken during
the conflict with England in 1388,
holding on to just a few pockets of land
around Calais and a handful of coastal
strongholds, including Bordeaux, rather
than the broad swaths lost earlier in
the war. In achieving this, Charles V
had reversed the losing trend and
boosted national morale, which had been
ground down by years of losses.
Alongside his successful management of
the conflict, Charles V also had a
significant internal impact on the
nation. This included steps towards more
professional, regular, supervised forces
and efforts to curb the free companies,
which removed the need for bands of
unruly mercenaries who had flourished
previously. Though the clearest
crown-led standardization of
recruitment, supervision, and pay came
later under Charles VII, notably through
ordinances beginning in 1439. Their
activities during time off from service
had often included pillaging rural
areas, which understandably upset local
populations. Reduction of the economic
deficit was achieved, as well as
internal reforms strengthening the state
in the wake of the devastation of the
Black Death. These helped stabilize the
nation and consolidate Valois house
rule, of which Charles himself was only
the second monarch, so by no means yet a
secure dynasty. However, despite his
best efforts, they would not account for
the poor leadership of his son, a trend
seen now all too often over the previous
centuries. Charles VI succeeded his
father at 11 years old. He was initially
under the custodianship of his two
uncles. However, no sooner had he begun
to forge his own path at the age of 20
that mental illness struck. After he
began asserting personal rule in 1388,
his first major attack struck in 1392,
and he would suffer from bouts of mania
and delusion for the remainder of his
life, seriously affecting his ability to
rule. Consequently, during his turbulent
reign, many of the territorial gains
secured by his father were lost to a
resurgent England. This losing trend
would climax at the Battle of Agincourt,
where in October 1415, France suffered
one of its most famous military defeats
of the war.
Despite being numerically inferior,
English forces made effective use of the
longbow, with as many as 80% of their
troops in this role. With English
archers forming the bulk of the army in
many accounts, firing off huge volumes
of arrows at ranges greater than the
French archers were capable of, the
English were given a distinct advantage.
At the end of the proceedings, up to
6,000 French lay dead. This included a
significant portion of the French
nobility from across the nation, which
would have its own local impacts on
regional governance and land ownership.
The decisive defeat led King Charles the
Sixth to agree to harsh peace terms with
English King Henry the Fifth, which
essentially signed over rights to the
French throne to England following his
death. These terms were later formalized
in the Treaty of Troyes in 1420, which
recognized Henry the Fifth and his heirs
as successors and disinherited the
Dauphin. This was a situation not
encountered even at the height of the
Angevin Empire's territorial hold over
French territory, and would take a
capable monarch to address. The man
tasked with this was Charles the
Seventh. Inheriting the legacy of his
father's troubled reign, he would manage
to turn the tide of the war with England
and with it the fate of the nation. This
was seen most dramatically in the
lifting of the siege of Orléans, which
involved the notable contribution of the
soon-to-be later celebrated as a
national heroine of the nation, Joan of
Arc. The English had besieged the
important city in 1428 and it looked
likely to fall. It wasn't until the
arrival of Joan, the peasant who said
she was guided by visions, that fortunes
would turn. She had sought direct
permission from King Charles VII to
pursue her mission of driving back the
English and within days of her entering
the city, the French forces inside had
managed to break out and end the siege.
After she entered Orléans on April 30th,
1429,
a series of aggressive assaults followed
and by May 8th, the English withdrew, a
turning point both militarily and
psychologically. While Joan's exact role
remains unclear, she clearly had a
significant effect on troop morale,
which was relevant not just to Orléans,
but the remainder of the war. Her value
as a symbol for the nation and rallying
point for an emerging nationalism was
even greater.
Capitalizing on this national victory
and momentum, Charles would be crowned
in Reims, capital in 1429 with Joan of
Arc in attendance as a standard-bearer.
The next decades were characterized by a
decline in English fortunes with Spain
recapturing much of its lost territory.
This process would culminate at the
Battle of Formigny in 1450.
Here, the English force was shattered
with many killed or captured. This was
compounded in 1453 by another decisive
French victory at the Battle of
Castillon, this time in Aquitaine.
With a similar number of English killed
or captured, it dealt a fatal blow to
their remaining capabilities. Both of
these engagements saw some of the
earliest deployments of new artillery
technology, which, though used in sieges
previously, had never been deployed
effectively in mobile battle before.
It would go on to become a defining
feature of all subsequent European
warfare.
Though Castillon brought an end to
hostilities, the war wouldn't be
formally concluded until the settlement
at Picquigny in 1475,
and England would still retain Calais
until 1558.
A great success overseen by Charles VII
as an important stepping stone for the
nation. In contrast to this bloody
conflict, which had been playing out for
over a century, the Renaissance had also
been gathering pace. Though France would
take some decades to recover from the
effects of the war, by the end of the
15th and early 16th centuries, it was
fully involved in this now Europe-wide
movement. Spreading out from the
developed Italian city-states, the
Renaissance placed a renewed emphasis on
classic literature and great works from
the period, ushering in a flourishing of
the arts, sciences, and other areas of
civic life. It brought about an
architectural transition from pure
Gothic to Renaissance styles, seen
across churches and other grand
buildings of the era. The influence of
great masters, such as Leonardo da
Vinci, was also felt, with his designs
featured in a well-known double
helix-style staircase at Château de
Chambord, often linked to Leonardo in
later tradition, though the attribution
is debated. He, in fact, took up
residence in France at the request of
King Francis I himself.
At the Château du Clos Lucé in 1516,
here, the now frail old man would
reportedly arrive with masterpieces,
including the Mona Lisa,
which it is believed he brought with him
and continued to refine in France. A
later tradition, but symbolic of
Francis' place in this important
movement. This was a new age with an
increased emphasis placed on humanism
and man's reasoning ability, marking a
turning point from some of the
superstitions of previous eras. New
universities were established, which in
turn helped to cement Francis' place as
a major center of education. This was
supported by the rise of new
technologies, such as the printing
press, which allowed for the
dissemination of literature much more
widely than before.
While for the rural poor, the effects
were less widely felt than the urban
middle and upper classes, a key impact
which reached them was the growth of
regional towns and cities. These had
been fueled by a boom in Renaissance
trade and provided exit options for
those wishing to leave the agricultural
economy. Over the coming centuries, many
would take this route, swelling the
ranks of the urban poor in growing towns
across the country. Many would
eventually transition into the newly
springing up trades which were
represented by their numerous trade
guilds. These were often powerful groups
and included artisans such as masons,
blacksmiths, carpenters, and others.
Another less direct result of the
Renaissance, which would certainly be
felt nationwide and across social
classes, was the emerging Protestant
faith. Unsurprisingly, the Renaissance
period with its increased emphasis on
reason and man's individual capability
to apply it had led many to taking this
approach towards religion and biblical
study. In turn, this had seen the rise
of a more personal interpretation of the
faith with authority received directly
through scripture rather than mediated
by the church in the middle.
The printing press and growing access to
personal Bibles in people's native
languages instead of Latin also fuels
the trend.
This emerging religious movement would
see a huge shift across Europe and usher
in a period of violent religious wars.
In stark contrast to Renaissance ideals
which had dominated for the previous
period, this oncoming cycle of conflict
would cause heavy loss of life and
contribute to severe economic strain for
France.
Protestantism had been ushered in by
initial figures like Martin Luther in
Germany with others such as Frenchman
John Calvin subsequently taking up the
cause.
By the mid-16th century, it had gathered
a significant following and posed a
serious threat to the Catholic Church
far greater than the Cathar heresy
suppressed in the medieval Albigensian
Crusade.
Though repression had been ongoing
against Protestants since the 1530s
under the otherwise liberal Francis I,
the situation would erupt into broader
conflict in 1562 following the massacre
at Vassy. Here, Catholic troops killed
Protestant worshipers leading to a
complex series of violent outbreaks
across the country over the coming
decades. The conflict also saw the
involvement of many outside states.
These included Spain and the Papacy on
the Catholic side and support from
England, the Dutch, and some German
Protestant princes on the Huguenot's
side, illustrating the pan-European
nature of this schism.
The Wars of Religion left death toll
estimates that vary widely, with some
estimates running into the millions once
famine and diseases are included.
Considering France's population was
around 16 million total in 1560, this
was a devastating proportion. The wars
were overseen by the last three kings
from the Valois house, with it helping
to cement the end of the dynasty. Henry
III was the last of these, and befitting
of the turbulent times, was assassinated
by an individual motivated by religion.
His replacement was a distant cousin,
the King of Navarre, who would assume
the title of Henry the IV and the French
crown in 1589, and to many in France's
dismay, maintain his Protestant faith.
He did so for four years, resisting the
efforts of the Catholic League, until
eventually choosing to convert to
Catholicism. He was reported as saying
of this that "Paris is well worth a
mass." A pragmatic approach, and an
example of the pragmatic statesmanship
he would display throughout his reign.
Crucially, Henry would issue the Edict
of Nantes in 1598, which ended the Wars
of Religion by granting Protestants the
right to practice their faith. Another
pragmatic choice, which drew to a close
the bloody chapter, allowing France to
rebuild as a nation and begin to look
outwards again into the 17th century. A
new age was now upon Europe, that of
global exploration. Columbus's discovery
of the Americas in 1492 had opened the
floodgates to discoveries here,
alongside new areas of interest along
the coast of West Africa, and
increasingly Asia.
While France had played a role in these
early chapters with pioneers like
Jacques Cartier establishing a French
stake in the St. Lawrence area, it had
been the Spanish ruler under the
Habsburg dynasty who had dominated this
early colonial period. With their
lucrative colonies in Central and South
America, they bolstered their position
in Europe. However, with France now
emerging from the chaos of the previous
decades and with a recovering economy,
they were in a position to develop their
colonial assets. This included their
primary focus on North America and
increasing hold over the Great Lakes
region, which also encompassed areas of
the West Indies and increasingly
lucrative plantation colonies reliant on
enslaved labor there.
By the time of the death of the second
Bourbon monarch, Louis the 13th, in
1643,
New France was still primarily a series
of trading posts. The population of
French settlers was still only in the
hundreds and most of the work collecting
the prized beaver pelts was done by
native allies whom French traders then
purchased from.
Under the reign of Louis the 14th,
though, and with increased state
measures to boost settlement, this began
to change. In the 1680s, settlers drove
south opening up the Louisiana area to
the French crown, which would remain a
core part of New France for nearly a
century. In 1682,
René Robert Cavelier, Sieur de La Salle,
claims the Mississippi basin for France
as Louisiana and subsequent decades saw
expanding French movement and fort
building through the interior.
Collectively, France's rapidly expanding
colonial holdings helped bring in wealth
to to crown, repairing economic damage
from the previous century, as well as
cementing the nation's place as a
powerful global player. Alongside the
decline of the Habsburgs since their
loss in the Thirty Years War and Spain's
fall from dominance in Europe, new
opportunities were opening up for the
ascendant France. Louis the XIV's long
reign of over 70 years helped capitalize
on these opportunities, despite also
being described as the high point of
absolute monarchical power. At home, he
was an active reformer, modernizing the
state and centralizing the greatest
amount of power around a monarch yet
achieved. Nobles' already diminished
influence was further reduced at Louis'
gain, as was that of the church. This
further cemented absolute power in the
monarch's hand, and along with many of
Louis' court's splendor and scale at
Versailles, in many ways contributed to
long-term pressures that would later
feed into revolution.
On the religious front, he revoked many
Protestant rights in the Edict of
Fontainebleau in 1685.
While the motivations for this aren't
fully clear, it rolled back much of the
peacemaking carried out by his
grandfather and first Bourbon monarch,
Henry the IV, who granted these rights
to end the bloody French Wars of
Religion.
As a result, many Protestants converted
to Catholicism, while a significant
other number of Huguenots fled to either
other Protestant European states or the
Americas. These had been centuries of
great transformation. From facing a
profound crisis with Charles VI nearly
signing over the kingdom to the English
at the height of the Hundred Years' War
to a France now projecting power
globally and centrally controlled by a
powerful ruler. The previously
autonomous regional nobles have been
largely reined in, and an intricate
state apparatus was developing.
Into the next era and the 1700s, France
would rise to the height of its global
power.
However, new challenges lay ahead with
the revolution and Napoleon soon to
follow.
The maps in our videos, those are the
light versions. For our shop, we take
the same research and go all in. Finer
line work, higher resolution, extra
texture, geographic details that would
get lost in a video. These are built for
people who wants the real thing.
Something you can reference, hang up, or
just own because it's the version we
actually wanted to make. The kind of map
you don't scroll past, you keep. Check
your favorite on our website at
knowledgeia.co or by clicking the link
in the description.